<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.1">Jekyll</generator>
<link href="http://blog.jdonado.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
<link href="http://blog.jdonado.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
<updated>2017-05-27T10:32:03+02:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.jdonado.com/</id>
<title>JDonado's Readme</title>
<subtitle>Coding in English, thinking in Spanish, living in Germany</subtitle>
<author>
<name>F. Javier R. Donado</name>
<email>jdonado@jdonado.com</email>
<uri>http://www.jdonado.com</uri>
</author>
<entry>
<title>Restore clover using Windows</title>
<link href="http://blog.jdonado.com/restore-clover/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Restore clover using Windows" />
<published>2017-05-26T00:00:00+02:00</published>
<updated>2017-05-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.jdonado.com/restore-clover</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.jdonado.com/restore-clover/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;restore-your-configplist&quot;&gt;Restore your config.plist&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clover is a boot manager that allows you to select the OS you want to boot with. It is used mostly by Hackintosh users, that is, people that install MacOSX (along with other OSs, like Linux and Windows) on a non-Apple machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Clover configuration can be quite tricky, and if you’re not lucky you can easily mess it up. That’s why it’s more than advisable to keep a backup of the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/EFI/CLOVER/config.plist&lt;/code&gt; configuration file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you happen to break down your MacOSX boot, but you still have a working Windows boot on the same machine, you can follow these steps in order to restore a backup of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;config.plist&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open an administrator console (run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cmd.exe&lt;/code&gt; as Administrator) and type the following:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;diskpart&lt;/code&gt; (open diskpart)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;list disk&lt;/code&gt; (list your hard drives with)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;select disk 1&lt;/code&gt; (select the disk where your Clover EFI boot has been installed. 1 is just an example)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;list partition&lt;/code&gt; (list the partitions available on the selected disk)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;select partition 1&lt;/code&gt; (select the boot EFI partition)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;assign letter=s&lt;/code&gt; (assign a letter. S in this case)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;exit&lt;/code&gt; (exit diskpart)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;s:&lt;/code&gt; (go to the just mounted boot partition)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd EFI\CLOVER\&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;copy c:\backups\config.plist .&lt;/code&gt; (c:\backups is just an example. Replace this path by the path where you have your config.plist backup)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If everything worked fine, you can now restart and use your MacOSX boot again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to that, some Clover prefixes that can help you find out what went wrong are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-x&lt;/code&gt; start using the safe mode&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-v&lt;/code&gt; verbose mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find more information about Hackintosh and Clover on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tonymacx86.com/&quot;&gt;tonymac86&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<category term="clover" />
<category term="hackintosh" />
<category term="clover" />
<category term="windows" />
<summary>Restore your config.plist</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>About Functional Programming</title>
<link href="http://blog.jdonado.com/about-fp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About Functional Programming" />
<published>2017-03-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
<updated>2017-03-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.jdonado.com/about-fp</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.jdonado.com/about-fp/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I’ve been doing some research on the topic of functional programming. I think it’s a good time to get together some of the resources I’ve found so far, and remark the ideas that motivated me to learn more about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-functional-programming&quot;&gt;Why Functional Programming?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading articles, books and watching videos by Eric Eliott, Brian Lonsdorf, Michael Fogus, Brian Beckman and others, I’ve convinced myself about the following facts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Object Oriented Design and Relational Databases potentially have a big problem: they bind your software and your data together with a very rigid structure that is very difficult to modify in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You usually have to make decisions about that rigid structure at a development stage where you simply don’t have all the relevant information. Requirements change with time and rigid structures don’t like changes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s almost impossible to design a very good OOD or RDB from the very beginning because &lt;strong&gt;humans cannot predict future&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I think not just functional programming but also NoSQL databases are getting more and more traction. Now that memory and computational power are getting bigger and cheaper, they are becoming a great alternative for many applications. In addition to that, functional techniques present clear advantages in distributed computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fight-complexity&quot;&gt;Fight complexity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/ZhuHCtR3xq8?t=17m13s&quot;&gt;Brian Beckman said&lt;/a&gt;, today in the software development community, we’re out of control in the complexity space. &lt;strong&gt;The way to control complexity is compositionality&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functional programming is probably the natural alternative to the classical object oriented paradigm. It’s been around since the very beginning of computation, but for some reason it never went mainstream. Until now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JavaScript is (maybe alongside with Scala) the first mainstream programming language that provides basic tools for developing software based partially &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eetWam3nhoM&quot;&gt;or even completely&lt;/a&gt; on the functional paradigm. Functions are first class citizens, you can create high order functions, and you can do many other things that were not possible in any of the older classic mainstream programming languages (such as C++, Java or C#). Interestingly enough, now that functional programming is becoming something cool and more and more people are interested about it, also the classic OOP languages are incorporating functional features to them, which is great! In fact, I think there’s great potential in combining both paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But functional programming can be quite tricky to understand in the beginning. It has its roots in lambda calculus (or cathegory theory, as you prefer), and it’s full of rather esoteric terms such as monoids, monads, functors, applicative functors, and so on. But the main idea behind it is very simple: &lt;strong&gt;build software just by writing small pieces of code (functions) that perform very specific tasks&lt;/strong&gt; and then compose them in order to provide a more complex behaviour. One of the main advantages of such an approach is that unit testing is much easier, sometimes even trivial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-steps&quot;&gt;First Steps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic and easy stuff first, please. The series on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL0zVEGEvSaeEd9hlmCXrk5yUyqUag-n84&quot;&gt;functional programming in JavaScript&lt;/a&gt; by MPJ are a great starting point. If you never heard of high order functions, Map, Reduce, Currying, and some other related concepts, you can find a quick and fun introduction here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-want-more-of-this&quot;&gt;I Want More of This&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After convincing myself of the conveninence of functions like Map and Reduce, I wanted to learn more. I found two very interesting books about functional programming with JavaScript:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.de/Functional-JavaScript-Introducing-Programming-Underscore-js/dp/1449360726&quot;&gt;Functional JavaScript&lt;/a&gt;, by Michael Fogus, is a comprehensive introduction to the main functional programming concepts. It focuses on JavaScript and the Underscore library. Concepts like purity, immutability, recursion, trampoline techniques, and currying are very well explained, with lots of examples.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MostlyAdequate/mostly-adequate-guide&quot;&gt;Professor Frisby’s Mostly Adequate Guide to Functional Programming&lt;/a&gt;, by Brian Lonsdorf (AKA Dr. Boolean). It’s not finished yet but, hey! it’s free!!. It shows a way to develop JavaScript that, in my humble opinion, is closer to what you might expect when working with more purely functional oriented programming languages, like Scala or even Haskell. It’s related to the three videos series &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h_tkIpwbsxY&amp;amp;list=PLK_hdtAJ4KqX0JOs_KMAmUNTNMRYhWEaC&quot;&gt;Classroom Coding with Prof. Frisby&lt;/a&gt; (very interesting too, but also very dense. You might need to watch them twice to get all the concepts). You can also find many other interesting talks on youtube from this author.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to start writing functional routines in your JavaScript applications, in the sense that was explained on “Functional Javascript”, &lt;a href=&quot;https://lodash.com/&quot;&gt;Lodash&lt;/a&gt; (a more performant alternative to Underscore) is a great library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to explore a more pure functional programming style, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lodash/lodash/tree/4.17.4-npm/fp&quot;&gt;lodash/fp&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ramdajs.com/&quot;&gt;Ramda&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://folktalejs.org/&quot;&gt;Folktale&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fantasyland/fantasy-land&quot;&gt;Fantasy Land&lt;/a&gt; are wonderful resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that’s not functional enough for you, you can give a try at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.purescript.org/&quot;&gt;PureScript&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://clojurescript.org/&quot;&gt;ClojureScript&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-bit-more-advanced&quot;&gt;A Bit More Advanced&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZhuHCtR3xq8&quot;&gt;Brian Beckman: Don’t fear the Monad&lt;/a&gt;. Brian Beckman (Princeton University, Microsoft, Amazon…) gives you a glimpse about the category theory behind monoids and monads, expressed in practical terms, familiar to an imperative programmer (he also gives C# examples). I find particularly interesting the following ideas:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Functions can be seen as data. You can model (almost) any function as a dictionary table where a lookup is performed.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Short story about the two separated camps created when computing started: the imperative one (tradition that led to languages like Fortran, C, Pascal, Java, etc.), where Math theory was put aside and performance was king, and the functional one (this one led to languages like Algol, Lisp, Smalltalk or Haskell), where they started out with Math theory (lambda calculus) and went from there down to the machine, sometimes at the expense of performance.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Build complexity out of simplicity by composing functions, not by adding ad-hoc features.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
<category term="functional-programming" />
<category term="functional-programming" />
<category term="javascript" />
<summary>Introduction</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Unit Testing in Angular 2: Common Exceptions</title>
<link href="http://blog.jdonado.com/unit-testing-in-angular-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unit Testing in Angular 2: Common Exceptions" />
<published>2017-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
<updated>2017-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.jdonado.com/unit-testing-in-angular-2</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.jdonado.com/unit-testing-in-angular-2/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;unit-testing-in-angular-2-common-exceptions&quot;&gt;Unit Testing in Angular 2: Common Exceptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working on an Angular 2 project (&lt;a href=&quot;http://angularjs.blogspot.de/2016/12/ok-let-me-explain-its-going-to-be.html?utm_content=bufferec238&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_source=facebook.com&amp;amp;utm_campaign=buffer&quot;&gt;or Angular 3, or 4, or whatever…&lt;/a&gt;) during the last couple of months, and I’m still learning how to unit test a project based in this new framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to share with you some of the most common exceptions I’ve found when first writing unit tests, and the solutions to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;problem-your-directive-name-is-not-a-known-element&quot;&gt;Problem: ‘your-directive-name’ is not a known element&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: import the component where &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;your-directive-name&lt;/code&gt; is defined and include it into the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;declarations&lt;/code&gt; field of the TestBed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;problem-cant-bind-to-ngmodel-since-it-isnt-a-known-property-of-input&quot;&gt;Problem: Can’t bind to ‘ngModel’ since it isn’t a known property of ‘input’&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: import &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;FormsModule&lt;/code&gt; and include it into the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;imports&lt;/code&gt; field of the TestBed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;problem-no-provider-for-yourservice&quot;&gt;Problem: No provider for YourService!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: import &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YourService&lt;/code&gt; and include it into the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;providers&lt;/code&gt; of the TestBed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same error can appear if you need Http: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;No provider for Http!&lt;/code&gt;. The same solution applies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;problem-no-provider-for-connectionbackend&quot;&gt;Problem: No provider for ConnectionBackend!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That appears when you test components or services where Http requests are performed.
Solution: import &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ConnectionBackend&lt;/code&gt; and include it together with the rest of providers of the TestBed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;problem-no-provider-for-requestoptions&quot;&gt;Problem: No provider for RequestOptions!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: import &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;HttpModule&lt;/code&gt; and include it into the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;imports&lt;/code&gt; of TestBed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;example&quot;&gt;Example&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s some code for a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;HomeComponent&lt;/code&gt; unit test, that uses a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;LoginComponent&lt;/code&gt; and loads a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SessionService&lt;/code&gt;, requiring &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Http&lt;/code&gt; and all the aforementioned dependencies in a single example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just want to illustrate how to load and specify the dependencies needed in order to bootstrap a test with them and the associated errors if any of these steps are missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not an example about how to test a component (that would be subject for another post). What we test here is just whether the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;HomeComponent&lt;/code&gt; component is successfully created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% highlight javascript %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;/* tslint:disable:no-unused-variable */
import { async, ComponentFixture, TestBed } from ‘@angular/core/testing’;
import { By } from ‘@angular/platform-browser’;
import { DebugElement } from ‘@angular/core’;
import { FormsModule } from ‘@angular/forms’;
import { SessionService } from ‘../../services/session.service’;
import { Http, HttpModule, Headers, RequestMethod, RequestOptions, Response, ConnectionBackend } from ‘@angular/http’;
import { HomeComponent } from ‘./home.component’;
import { LoginComponent } from ‘../login/login.component’;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;describe(‘HomeComponent’, () =&amp;gt; {
  let component: HomeComponent;
  let fixture: ComponentFixture&lt;homecomponent&gt;;&lt;/homecomponent&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;beforeEach(async(() =&amp;gt; {
    TestBed.configureTestingModule({
      imports: [FormsModule, HttpModule],
      providers: [SessionService, Http, ConnectionBackend],
      declarations: [HomeComponent, LoginComponent]
    })
      .compileComponents();
  }));&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;beforeEach(() =&amp;gt; {
    fixture = TestBed.createComponent(HomeComponent);
    component = fixture.componentInstance;
    fixture.detectChanges();
  });&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;it(‘exists’, () =&amp;gt; {
    expect(component).toBeTruthy();
  });
});&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% endhighlight %}&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<category term="coding" />
<category term="angular" />
<category term="angular2" />
<category term="unit" />
<category term="testing" />
<summary>Unit Testing in Angular 2: Common Exceptions</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Inheritance in AngularJS, again</title>
<link href="http://blog.jdonado.com/inheritance-in-angularjs-again/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inheritance in AngularJS, again" />
<published>2016-10-23T00:00:00+02:00</published>
<updated>2016-10-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.jdonado.com/inheritance-in-angularjs-again</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.jdonado.com/inheritance-in-angularjs-again/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;rethinking-about-inheritance-in-angularjs-15&quot;&gt;Rethinking about inheritance in AngularJS 1.5&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;{% link _posts/2016-08-06-inheritance-and-observer-pattern-in-angular-js.markdown %}&quot;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt; I showed an example about how could inheritance be implemented in an AngularJS project, using Javascript (ECMAScript 5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that example I used it to implement the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Observer_pattern&quot;&gt;observer pattern&lt;/a&gt; in different services without having to define the same functions again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is a common problem when dealing with the (now old) ECMAScript 5, as long as you want to avoid code repetition and structure your code in a similar fashion as you would with a pure object oriented language, such as Java or C#.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, you can sort of implement classical inheritance in Javascript. &lt;em&gt;But should you?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After thinking about it and trying out many experiments, I decided it’s not really worth it, since &lt;strong&gt;it complicates your code and makes it more difficult to read and maintain&lt;/strong&gt;. But of course, &lt;strong&gt;repeating the code is no solution either&lt;/strong&gt;. So maybe we can find an easier solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we shouldn’t fight against the language we’re using: it’s very tiring and at the end of the day it’s going to make our code worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to do something the language was not designed for is somehow fighting against it. Instead of that, a better solution would be using the native characteristics of that language to fulfill our goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javascript provides many alternatives to classical inheritance if you’re willing to embrace prototypal inheritance. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/javascript-scene/common-misconceptions-about-inheritance-in-javascript-d5d9bab29b0a&quot;&gt;Eric Eliott has many very interesting articles about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I come with an alternative solution that worked for me with AngularJS services. The idea is a service with a toolset of constructors, implementing the code of the objects we may want to use again and again. Something like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Factory_method_pattern&quot;&gt;factory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% highlight javascript %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘use strict’;
angular.module(‘exampleApp’, [])
  .service(‘factoryService’, [function () {
    return {
      // Observer is going to be our constructor
      Observer: function () {
        var observer = {},
          observerCallbacks = [];&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;    observer.registerObserverCallback = function (callback) {
      if (typeof callback !== &quot;function&quot;) {
        return;
      }
      observerCallbacks.push(callback);
    };

    observer.unregisterObserverCallback = function (callback) {
      var found = -1;
      observerCallbacks.forEach(function (element, idx) {
        if ((element + '') === (callback + '')) {
          found = idx;
        }
      });
      if (found !== -1) {
        this.observerCallbacks.splice(found, 1);
      }
    };

    observer.notifyObservers = function () {
      angular.forEach(this.oberverCallbacks, function (callback) {
        callback();
      });
    };

    return observer;
  } // end: Observer constructor
};   }]);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% endhighlight %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on how many constructors you want to define, you can have different factory services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you want to create a new service that implements the functions defined in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Observer&lt;/code&gt;, you can do something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% highlight javascript %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;angular.module(‘exampleApp’, [])
  .service(‘NewService’, [‘factoryService’, function (factoryService) {
    // New object using the constructor defined in the factory
    var observable = new factoryService.Observer();
    return {
      observable: observable,
      otherStuff: [‘service’, ‘specific’, ‘things’]
    };
  }]);&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% endhighlight %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way, you will have a property in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NewService&lt;/code&gt; that’s called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;observable&lt;/code&gt;, on which you can call the functions of an &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Observer&lt;/code&gt; object that only exists in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NewService&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have not repeated the code of the functions defined in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Observable&lt;/code&gt; and the code is easier to understand and maintain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think about this approach? Would you prefer &lt;a href=&quot;{% link _posts/2016-08-06-inheritance-and-observer-pattern-in-angular-js.markdown %}&quot;&gt;the other one&lt;/a&gt;? Do you see any potential problems when doing something like this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<category term="coding" />
<category term="angularjs" />
<category term="inheritance" />
<category term="ecmascript5" />
<summary>Rethinking about inheritance in AngularJS 1.5</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>ng-show and ng-animate</title>
<link href="http://blog.jdonado.com/ng-show-and-ng-animate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ng-show and ng-animate" />
<published>2016-08-08T00:00:00+02:00</published>
<updated>2016-08-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.jdonado.com/ng-show-and-ng-animate</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.jdonado.com/ng-show-and-ng-animate/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;if-ng-show-happens-to-be-too-slow-without-an-obvious-reason&quot;&gt;If ng-show happens to be too slow without an obvious reason&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It happened to me tonight that ng-show was taking too long to refresh. I’ve read about &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/19177732/what-is-the-difference-between-ng-if-and-ng-show-ng-hide&quot;&gt;the differences between ng-if and ng-show&lt;/a&gt; and how sometimes ng-show can decrease performance. But in this case it was a pretty straightforward example, and it shouldn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end it turned out to be the combination of ng-show and ng-animate. I wasn’t using any animation, but there was a css transition running anyway, and making things look slower than they were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any of this ever happens to you, and you don’t want to remove ng-animate from your project, simply add the .no-animate class to the element where ng-show or ng-hide is used, and update your css with the following lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% highlight css %}
.ng-animate.no-animate {
  transition: 0s none;
  -webkit-transition: 0s none;
  animation: 0s none;
  -webkit-animation: 0s none;
}
{% endhighlight %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As simple as that.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<category term="coding" />
<category term="angularjs" />
<summary>If ng-show happens to be too slow without an obvious reason</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Inheritance and Observer Pattern in AngularJS 1.4</title>
<link href="http://blog.jdonado.com/inheritance-and-observer-pattern-in-angular-js/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inheritance and Observer Pattern in AngularJS 1.4" />
<published>2016-06-12T00:00:00+02:00</published>
<updated>2016-06-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.jdonado.com/inheritance-and-observer-pattern-in-angular-js</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.jdonado.com/inheritance-and-observer-pattern-in-angular-js/">&lt;p&gt;In AngularJS, when designing services, it is well common to return an instance of the &lt;strong&gt;$http&lt;/strong&gt; service. The code that requests it (usually within a controller), must process then the promise and do whatever it is to be done with the data that come from server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like in this example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% highlight javascript %}
‘use strict’;
angular.module(‘exampleApp’, [])
  .service(‘ItemsService’, [‘$http’, function ($http) {
    this.getItems = function () {
      return $http.get(‘www.myapi-url.com/items’);
    };
  }])
  .controller(‘ExampleController’, [‘ItemsService’, function (ItemsService) {
    var self = this;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;this.itemsList = []; // A property of the controller stores an array with items, initially empty.

ItemsService.getItems().then(
  function (data) {
    self.itemsList = data.data;
  },
  function (error) {
    console.log(&quot;There has been an error&quot; + error);
  }
);   }]);             {% endhighlight %}            
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, sometimes you just don’t want to handle the server information in the controller, because you might need to do it in many other places in your app, and you don’t want to repeat the same code in your controllers. After all, it seems reasonable that any processing related to your items (filters, date parsing or whatever you need to do) can be encapsulated in that ItemsService, so that you can reuse it easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specially if it is something that must be done over and over, because the API you’re working with doesn’t exactly give you back what you need or in the format that you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, you might want to reduce the number of http requests your app performs, and storing these data as a property of the service might be convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution-the-observer-pattern&quot;&gt;Solution: the Observer Pattern&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I thought it could be a good idea to implement the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Observer_pattern&quot;&gt;observer pattern&lt;/a&gt; in angular services that retrieve information from server, store it and manipulate it in some way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you want to implement this pattern in more than one service, it is better to define it just once and create a new service that inherits that pattern whenever necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since inheritance is something that can be a bit tricky when using Javascript, and even more if you want to combine it with Angular, I thought it might be useful to other people if I shared my solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve created &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fjrd84/notes-app&quot;&gt;a git repository&lt;/a&gt; with a complete working example. Next, I’ll describe briefly how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-observable-service-parent&quot;&gt;The Observable Service (Parent)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a service is declared with the functions that implement the observable pattern. But instead of returning a JSON, as usual in an AngularJS service, we return a function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% highlight javascript %}
angular.module(‘notesApp’)
  .factory(‘observableService’, function () {
    // A constructor is defined in order to create further services that extend this functionality
    return function () {
      this.observerCallbacks = [];
      //register an observer
      this.registerObserverCallback = function (callback) {
        if (typeof callback !== “function”) {
          return;
        }
        this.observerCallbacks.push(callback);
      };
      //unregister an observer
      this.unregisterObserverCallback = function (callback) {
        var found = -1;
        this.observerCallbacks.forEach(function (element, idx) {
          if ((element + ‘’) === (callback + ‘’)) {
            found = idx;
          }
        });
        if (found !== -1) {
          this.observerCallbacks.splice(found, 1);
        }
      };
      this.notifyObservers = function () {
        angular.forEach(this.observerCallbacks, function (callback) {
          callback();
        });
      }
    };
  });
{% endhighlight %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;child-observable-service&quot;&gt;Child Observable Service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, in order to inherit these functions, you can simply do the following (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fjrd84/notes-app/blob/master/app/scripts/services/configuration-service.js&quot;&gt;extract from the file configuration-service.js&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% highlight javascript %}  &lt;br /&gt;
angular.module(‘notesApp’)
  .factory(‘configurationService’, function ($http, observableService) {
    var configService = {};
    // The config service inherits observable service
    configService = new observableService();&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;configService.someNewProperty = &quot;Initial Value&quot;;

return configService;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;}
{% endhighlight %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inheritable-service-that-inherits-the-observableservice&quot;&gt;Inheritable Service that Inherits the observableService&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need to create a service that inherits from the observableService, that is also inheritable by other services, you should return a function, instead of a JSON object. This is what we do in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fjrd84/notes-app/blob/master/app/scripts/services/basic-resource.js&quot;&gt;basic-resource.js&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% highlight javascript %}
angular.module(‘notesApp’)
  .factory(‘basicResource’, [‘observableService’, ‘$http’, ‘configurationService’,
    function (observableService, $http, configurationService) {&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;  var basicResource;

  // some private variables and functions can be added here
  var privateVar = &quot;privateValue&quot;;

  var privateFunction = function (){
    return &quot;privateFunction&quot;;
  };

  // The function you return works as the constructor of your class
  basicResource = function () {
    // In your new constructor, you apply the constructor of the class you want to inherit
    observableService.apply(this, arguments);
    var self = this;

    // here you define the properties of the service
    this.allElements = [];

    this.otherPublicProperty = &quot;Initial Value&quot;;

  };

  // We inherit from observableService now
  basicResource.prototype = new observableService();

  return basicResource;

}]); {% endhighlight %}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;controller-that-observes-services-that-inherit-from-observableservice&quot;&gt;Controller that Observes Services that Inherit from observableService&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you have observable services, you can simply define the callbacks in your controllers, and these will be updated whenever the service retrieves new information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% highlight javascript %}
 angular.module(‘notesApp’).controller(‘MainController’,
  [‘$scope’, ‘configurationService’, ‘notesService’,
    function ($scope, configurationService, notesService) {
      ‘use strict’;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;  var self = this;

  // Callback to be run when the configuration is ready
  var configurationReady = function () {
    notesService.loadElements();
  };

  // Callbacks to update the scope when new elements are available
  var updateNotes = function () {
    self.notes = notesService.allElements;
  };

  // Register observer callbacks
  notesService.registerObserverCallback(updateNotes);
  configurationService.registerObserverCallback(configurationReady);

  if (configurationService.isConfigurationReady()) {
    configurationReady();
  } else {
    // The observer has been registered: when ready, loadElements will be automatically called.
    configurationService.loadConfiguration();
  }

}]); {% endhighlight %}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was it. If you want to explore the complete repository, or even experiment with it and modify it, feel free to fork me on github: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fjrd84/notes-app&quot;&gt;https://github.com/fjrd84/notes-app&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<category term="coding" />
<category term="angularjs" />
<category term="design-patterns" />
<category term="observer" />
<category term="inheritance" />
<summary>In AngularJS, when designing services, it is well common to return an instance of the $http service. The code that requests it (usually within a controller), must process then the promise and do whatever it is to be done with the data that come from server.</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Special Thanks</title>
<link href="http://blog.jdonado.com/special-thanks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Special Thanks" />
<published>2016-06-12T00:00:00+02:00</published>
<updated>2016-06-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.jdonado.com/special-thanks</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.jdonado.com/special-thanks/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;acknowledgements&quot;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to specially thank the help of the following people when I was developing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jdonado.com&quot;&gt;www.jdonado.com&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maria Kouman&lt;/strong&gt;, who is always supportive with me during my long hours in front of the computer, giving also great feedback and wonderful ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Artur Beyrle&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://lexip-design.de&quot;&gt;(Lexip Design)&lt;/a&gt;, who crafted some layouts for my home page and provided me with an extraordinary feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marcel Scherer&lt;/strong&gt;, from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.netvico.com&quot;&gt;netvico GmbH&lt;/a&gt; who also helped me model the home page and gave me great advice about design.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Piotr Kulczycki&lt;/strong&gt;, who even while beta launching his amazing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.photler.com&quot;&gt;Photler&lt;/a&gt; kindly took some time to try out an early beta of this page and gave me fantastic feedback. If you want to see a brilliant travel photography site, check out his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldinmylens.com/&quot;&gt;World In My Lens&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rubén Álvarez&lt;/strong&gt;, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://chismeanimal.bandcamp.com/&quot;&gt;Chisme Animal&lt;/a&gt; who has always been for me, during many many years, a great source of ideas and inspiration, and provided me with feedback and material for building this site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have to thank the following people for contributing to the open source community, because their work has been particularly helpful for me when developing this web page: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/impress/impress.js&quot;&gt;Bartek Szopka&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/pmcgriff/pen/myKGZg&quot;&gt;Peter McGriff&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/blueimp/Gallery&quot;&gt;Sebastian Tschan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/dicson/pen/waKPgQ&quot;&gt;Dicson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/medemas/pen/QwvgEr&quot;&gt;Mason Medeiros&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SalGnt/Travelogue&quot;&gt;Dmitry Zelinsky and Salvatore Gentile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
<category term="coding" />
<category term="acknowledgements" />
<summary>AcknowledgementsI have to specially thank the help of the following people when I was developing www.jdonado.com:</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Hello World</title>
<link href="http://blog.jdonado.com/hello-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello World" />
<published>2016-03-28T00:00:00+02:00</published>
<updated>2016-03-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
<id>http://blog.jdonado.com/hello-world</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.jdonado.com/hello-world/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-jdonadocom&quot;&gt;What is jdonado.com?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jdonado.com&quot;&gt;Jdonado.com&lt;/a&gt; is my personal page, &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.jdonado.com&quot;&gt;blog.jdonado.com&lt;/a&gt; is this blog, and you’re very welcome to them both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My name is F. Javier R. Donado, I’m from Madrid (Spain) and I live in Stuttgart (Germany). I’m a software developer, and I also take pictures and record music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.jdonado.com&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; I write mostly about software development. In &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jdonado.com&quot;&gt;jdonado.com&lt;/a&gt; I describe my experience as a software developer, I show my pictures and my music, and I write about it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-you-do-it&quot;&gt;How did you do it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used AngularJS to develop &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jdonado.com&quot;&gt;www.jdonado.com&lt;/a&gt;. So actually, it’s not exactly a just page but a web app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is based in &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, and uses a slightly modified &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SalGnt/Travelogue&quot;&gt;Travelogue&lt;/a&gt; template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both projects are open source, so feel free to visit me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fjrd84&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Any feedback will be appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;did-you-do-it-all&quot;&gt;Did you do it all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For what you can see in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jdonado.com&quot;&gt;www.jdonado.com&lt;/a&gt;, mostly yes. Of course I used some plugins and snippets (I don’t think reinventing the wheel is a good idea), but apart from that, I took care about the rest (code, design, image editing…). I like to use it as a playground to try out new ideas. Check the &lt;a href=&quot;{% link _posts/2016-06-12-special-thanks.markdown %}&quot;&gt;Special Thanks&lt;/a&gt; post for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
<category term="coding" />
<category term="about" />
<category term="jdonado.com" />
<summary>What is jdonado.com?</summary>
</entry>
</feed>
